through service. Mr. Nisley.
>> Yeah. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Um, this
legislation is uh is pretty
straightforward. Um, back in February,
there was a an accident involving one of
the city's front load um, garbage trucks
that uh, rendered it inoperable. Um, the
truck has been in in uh, in in the shop
for quite some time now. Um, the city
has been has rented a new garbage truck
and we're paying currently $8,900 a
month for the rental. Um, not to
mention, um, the city, you know, the the
sanitation department anticipates in in
excess of $128,000 to fix the truck with
some, um, some hidden damage potentially
still yet to come. Um, and, uh, and with
with a timetable on parts looking at 10
months or more. um you know this the
service safety director the sanitation
department and I um believe that the
best the best case scenario for the city
would be to have the sanitation
department purchased a new vehicle which
this legislation uh appropriates the
funds necessary to do that. Um so that's
it.
Does anyone have any questions on that?
Okay, seeing none. So I have two
readings on here.
>> Yep. Two readings and council member
Hoop will be my second.
>> Great. Thank you. Now, not on the
agenda, we have a walk-in piece that
will come in tonight. That is going to
be temporary ordinance 826 that's coming
through law committee. Uh, Miss Smiley.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. So, this
is not as straightforward as the last
one. So, this piece of legislation came
to the law director, the law director's
office late last week. Um, and she
received it from Marian the developer
about the Viva Senior Living Complex
that's going to be located on Sloum in
West 7th and they are requesting
council's approval to vacate three
easements on that property. If the law
director could provide more context on
that, that would be wonderful.
>> Sure, happy to. So um
whenever you develop typically you get
something that's called an alta survey
um in order to satisfy the title
insurance company. When Marian did their
altter survey, they discovered that
there were three easements through the
parcels um between 7th Avenue and 8th
Avenue and Sloum and Hawking Street um
which is where they intend to develop
and build as u Miss Smiley said a large
I apologize I can't remember the number
um but quite a few um senior assisted
living um
houses in multi in multif family their
departments in multif family um
development. They're all going to be
right there. Um and the problem was that
the city's easements um indicated that
they could not be built on top of
previously. This land was platted in
1905 as Wright's addition. Um, and so it
took a little bit of digging to figure
out what had happened over the years and
why the um the exhibit that VA was
giving us did not match what the city's
records actually show. Um it would
appear that
the right of way was originally platted
in 1905 and then in 1952
um for some reason some of the
surrounding property owners decided that
they did not want to see those parcels
develop as individual lots. Um which I'm
guessing because in 1905 there probably
wasn't a lot of um FEMA control flood
plane type regulation that that sort of
thing. And this is in the 100-year flood
plane. So I would imagine in the 50s we
had figured out that it probably wasn't
going to be a good idea to build a bunch
of houses in this area. And so they
decided to kind of get rid of the
residential subdivision feel by getting
rid of that rightway so that they could
make these parcels larger and subdivide
them in a different fashion which is
what ultimately happened. Um when city
decided to vacate the right of way, they
decided to also reserve easements for
any infrastructure, any public
improvements that were already in the
right ofway. Um there was there was no
public improvements in the right of way
if you all want to refer to your map in
the alleys um that are indicated to the
west and to the east of what was
formerly Zayn Avenue. But Zayn Avenue
itself does have a 12-in sanitary sewer
line running down the middle of it. Um
the city engineer and water pollution
control have indicated that they're fine
with that line being abandoned um and
vacating that easement. Uh they no
longer need it. They have camered the
line. They have determined that it has
collapsed um partially and that also it
has absolutely no laterals connecting to
it from from any of the neighboring
properties. So it's unnecessary at this
point. Um, but the actual easement
that's that's really concerning is the
one to the west, which is between what
was formerly 8th Avenue and 7th Avenue.
Um, it sits underneath of where VA
intends to build their their multifamily
senior assisted living structure. And
obviously, um, if you're a title
company, you don't want to let people
build on a lot where they're where they
intend to put their building where
there's an easement that says you cannot
build here, right? Um, so they they
recently discovered this. They are also
bonding this project through the
Lancaster Port Authority. Uh, the reason
the timing is so import is important is
because the bonds will be issued on
April 15th. You don't meet again until
April 20th. Um, and like I said, this
was discovered fairly recently. Uh, as
you can tell from the from the handmade
exhibit that you have in front of you, I
sat down with markers this afternoon and
a ruler and made that. Typically, when I
ask you to do something property
related, right? When I'm asking you to
give up a property right or to claim a
property right, whatever, we do it with
a plat and meets and bounds survey that
show exactly what you're doing. Um,
unfortunately the exhibit that the
developer provided uh had some had some
land on there that honestly I don't know
I don't know that we have the ability to
do anything with anymore. Um but also it
had previously been subdivided. Like if
you look at the um the alley to the
east, you'll see there's lines that
continue up that are that are dashed
lines slash lines across that. um that
property has been either split again or
combined or something and I did not have
the time to go through the entire you
know chain of title to figure out what
happened and when it happened. Um and
they're not building on top of that. So
it doesn't make any difference to them.
Um also I had to be very careful. Um, I
wanted to make sure that
we maintain the easement that exists
from west to east on the former 8th
Avenue right ofway because we do have um
storm sewer infrastructure in that area.
Storm sewer infrastructure that is
scheduled to be replaced in the near
future. So, they will be reconstructing
across there as well. So, in the while
the exhibit shows the three easements
being vacated that are mentioned in the
prior um legislation from city council
50-52, I did indicate in your new
ordinance that you are specifically
maintaining um and not vacating the
easement that was created that runs the
full length and width of 8 the former
8th Avenue right ofway um that's that's
shown on the exhibit. So, I apologize.
This is kind of a mess. This is not
usually the quality of of something that
we we would bring in. Um, but it needs
to get done and it needs to get done
quickly. Um, Mike Huber, Council for the
Developer, is here tonight. If anybody
would like to ask any questions, um, if
if there's more information that you
think is necessary, um, he's here and
he's willing to assist with that.
Well, Director Hall, based on your
research today, were there any other
legal issues that we would you would
anticipate that we should know about?
>> No. Um, I wanted to make sure that the
easements were valid easements. They
were. I finally got um I finally got
proof of that from the recorder's office
late this afternoon. Um, so technically
they were valid easements, although I
will say again the city council of 1952
was kind of willy-nilly about how they
um reserved those easements in the first
place. They just said the width of the
ride of way, you know, that's it. But I
mean, that could be anything at this
point. Um, I don't know that we still
have a firm grasp on what that is. Um,
but again, the the developer doesn't
intend to build in the area that the
city needs in order to reconstruct our
our storm sewer line. So, I don't think
it's going to be an issue. I don't
think, you know, they're going to have
any issues with us doing this. Um, that
east to west line actually, I don't
believe runs under any of their pavement
either. Um, if there's an easement,
we're required to do the work and fix
whatever's on top of it, right? So, if
there's pavement already there, we're
required to go back and fix that as
well. it doesn't look like there's going
to be any pavement there um based on the
plans either. So there shouldn't be any
additional cost for fixing that as well.
Um so just something else to keep in
mind as you think about this.
>> I would like to invite the developer to
come up for additional questions. Thank
you.
>> Uh thank you Stephanie. Good evening um
council members. My name is Mike Huber.
Address 255 East Fifth Street,
Cincinnati, Ohio. I'm outside council
for Marian Development Group who is
developing this property as an assisted
affordable senior living facility. Um
Stephanie did a great job explaining all
that. Um I do apologize for the
emergency circumstances um of this, but
just to provide a little bit more
context for you all so that you all feel
comfortable um with this sort of last
second request here. So all of these
easements here are not currently serving
any other residents, any other
properties. um there are no active
utility lines running through them. Um
we also have our engineer here if there
are any engineering specific questions.
Um and a little bit about why this is
kind of coming up as such a big issue
now. Um in addition to it being
discovered on the Alta survey and in the
title work we did for the property. Um
there's also the issue of the bond
financing. Those bonds were actually
supposed to go out last week um via Miss
Stephanie Bosow's great office and the
great work that they do at the port. Um
if any of you are aware of current
events in our country, uh the bond
market has lost quite a bit of value in
the last two weeks. Um so getting these
bonds um issued as quickly as possible
is paramount for the economic viability
of the project both from a city and port
standpoint and from a private developer
standpoint. Um so any information I
could provide to make you all
comfortable with this last second
request. Um, we are needing this passed
as an emergency measure. Um, which I
know would forego the typical readings
you would see with these issues, but um,
as I've stated, these easements are not
currently serving any other property.
Nobody will use lose utility access um,
at any point. Utilities will be provided
uh to the facility there by the other
pathways available. Um, so if there are
any questions, I'm happy to answer them.
So the um what the law director alluded
to was that it was a very important
project. Could you talk to us about why
knowing that is going to be the one and
only version of this type of housing for
seniors in Lancaster and why that's
important?
>> Yeah. Yeah. I'm I'm racking my brain now
for when I when I did the original
zoning work uh almost a year and a half
ago when we sat down with the city um
and did all that work. So, I think as we
all know in Ohio broadly and especially
in central Ohio, um senior living is a
really dire need. Um I think on just
about every single housing inventory,
every single housing study I've seen,
especially in central Ohio, um senior is
a high need. Assisted senior is also a
very high need and a very rare need. Um
and it's being met exceptionally well
here by the Marian project. Um, I think
as city staff can attest when they've
seen the design plans and everything
else, um, these are akin to market rate
facilities. This would be the type of
facility that you drove through with um,
an elderly relative and said, "Wow,
you're going to get the best of
everything. You're going to have fully
amenitized experience um, and you're
going to get taken care of really well.
These are also local facilities. Most of
the residents in all of Marian's
facilities come from about a 3m radius.
Um, so this is not a use that draws a
lot of people in from Franklin County,
Montgomery County, Hamilton County. This
will impact the local Lancaster area.
It'll allow Lancaster residents to age
in place. Um, and it'll also allow them
to do so. um will it allow people who
would not normally have access to market
rate assisted living facilities um to
have access to these facilities and be
able to stay in their community um where
they feel safe where they feel welcome
um and age they're also tied to this
something I didn't mention um this does
receive OFA financing um which is also a
critical component to keeping OA happy
and keeping that process moving um with
the state
did that that answer.
>> What type of financing was that? What
does that mean?
>> OFA tax credit financing. So, Ohio
financing housing authority
>> provides tax credits for these types of
deals. Um, so the way that these are
financed for individuals who come um and
meet the AMI threshold um for not
essentially making enough money to be
able to afford a market rate assisted
living product. Um it's a combination of
OPA tax credit funding and then uh
Medicare waiverss.
>> That was the part I wanted to hear. Yep.
Yep. And then Medicare waiverss, that's
that's why you'll start seeing a lot
more of these in Ohio. That's a
relatively recent change uh the Ohio
legislature made a few years ago was to
allow Medicare waiverss to be used in
these contexts.
>> Yeah,
>> I have a few questions. Um if I may, um
how many units will will your facility
hold and what are the eligibility
requirements to be housed in your
facility?
>> I believe we are at 116
118. We're at 118. Two more than I
thought, which is awesome. And Stephanie
need to remind me of the eligibility. Is
it 60% AMI?
>> Yep. 60% AMI, 60% of the adjusted income
level threshold there. So, folks would
come apply, meet that threshold. Um,
with a combination of the Medicare
waiver from the state of funding, um,
they would come in at very, very low
rates. I apologize. I don't know what
the exact rate would be. Um but it is
affordable um to meet OHA's
requirements.
>> And uh do you have any age restrictions
on on the housing at your facility?
>> I believe they are all 55 and up. 55 and
up. My wonderful assistant Stephanie
Bosco over there.
>> So yeah, it's all 55 and up. The age
tends to skew much older. Um, anyone
who's familiar with assisted living,
it's that step between independent and
full nursing care. Um, so these are
folks that for the most part are able to
kind of go about their day with limited
assistance needed. Maybe somebody needs
to come and remind them to take their
pills. U maybe they have some mobility
issues. Um, but it's not the full
confined to a nursing bed. Um, but not
quite independent living.
Do you anticipate um how much do you
anticipate your units being what what's
the occupancy level do you think it's
going to um uh like how full do you
think your facility is going to be? You
know, that kind of thing.
>> Um I I think it's going to fill up. Um
as I mentioned before, these are this is
a very critically needed use basically
everywhere in Ohio. Um there are usually
waiting lists to get in these facilities
in the other states in which Marian
operates. Um, it's very rare to find a
assisted senior living facility that is
also affordable and that's also akin to
a market rate product. Um, these tend to
move up to the top of the list for a lot
of folks.
>> One final question.
>> Um, is is your project receiving any tax
abatements on the property? We are just
doing the Yes, we are
>> full%
for 15 years.
>> 100% for 15 years.
>> All right. Thank you.
>> Any other questions?
>> Can we get a copy of a drawing or print
for the building? Just just understand
how it's going to lay on this property.
>> Yeah.
pass it around
just to to back up for a second because
I there was a lot that was covered here
and I just want to try to simplify this
for some folks. make sure everybody
understands who might be watching from
home or u in the crowd. So I I guess the
reason we found these easements were
found kind of last I don't want to say
last minute but very late in the game.
>> Yes.
>> Due to the title company in the server.
Yeah.
>> Okay. So you started this process what
like over a year and a half ago and just
like within the last couple weeks this
is when they they popped up on some old
records I'm going to guess from the 50s.
>> That is my understanding. Um I
personally did not work as the sort of
transactional council. I was the uh
zoning council um for this project. So
once once that got underway, but it's my
understanding that um it was found out
rather late in the game. Um hence the
need to
>> tonight. And from what it appears these
three easements, there's nothing using
those easements right now. There's no
utilities whatsoever and nobody's
applied to to use these for any
purposes. So, as I said, the the one in
the middle, the former Zayn Avenue, that
does have a 12-in sanitary sewer line in
it right now, but they came it. They
determined that it is partially
collapsed and that none of the laterals
are actually connecting to any
neighborhood properties. So, they're
willing to just abandon
>> to rip it out. It's not working. It's
not a used
>> They're actually going to let Marian and
Va when they start their construction,
they're going to take it out for the
city of Lancaster.
>> Yeah.
>> All right.
>> Or abandon it. They could fill it as
well. It just however they want to get.
>> I mean, because it looks like there was
maybe a plan in the 50s or earlier to
put a development in here. I'm just
guessing by the where
>> like I said in 1905 it was platted as a
full subdivision and that's why all the
right of way was put in at that time.
>> Okay.
>> Yep.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah. It's not unusual. And there's a
statute now that was enacted after the
50s under Ohio law where most
municipalities or other townships,
counties when they vacate a ride ofway,
they'll often reserve a um easement
there usually because they've put public
utilities within the ride of way
previously they didn't need an easement
because it was in the right way, but
when they abandon the rideway and they
want to keep the utility line, okay,
they easement.
>> Thank you. I just wanted to cover that
again just to simplify it a little bit
for everybody.
Mr. OG,
>> uh, are you the one working on the
zoning and, uh,
finding these easements?
>> Um, I was zoning council, um, the
individuals who would been responsible
for finding the easements. Um, would be
a combination of the title company
providing title insurance for the
project and then the surveyor who would
have been contracted to survey the
property. about how many people would
have been involved with this?
>> Um
510 510
>> 510
510 maybe.
>> And you said you've been working on this
for a year and a half.
>> Marian has been engaged with this for
about a year and a half. um starting
with sort of the preliminary zoning
process and then preliminary engineering
and then as full engineering full scope
moves down the line um ramps up a little
bit in the development process.
>> Does Marian outsource
this kind of council
uh and like title work and that kind of
stuff?
>> Yes. Yep. They use outside council,
outside engineering firms and um outside
title companies. I'm just trying to
figure out who dropped the ball. Why
>> honestly like cut through it? Why was
this not found until last week?
>> That is something that we are still
determining ourselves um within that
process. I unfortunately don't have an
answer as to exactly when in the process
um that was missed um from our end. So I
apologize I can't give you a more
definite answer on that question.
All right. Any other questions?
>> All right. Thank you.
>> Thank you for your time.
>> And I'm asking for suspension. And the
reason I think that it's important for
the suspension even though I know that
we do not like to do this lightly and
we'd like those three readings for
transparency. This particular project is
important because it would be the first
and only option for seniors to be able
to use Medicaid um for in-house care and
and independent living and it's a really
important component for our community.
So, uh Mr. Skunover is going to be my
second.
>> Agreed. All right. Thank you. Uh we do
not have any new any additional new
resolutions or ordinances. So, we can
move on to department updates. anyone
the department update.
>> Yes, I wanted to let council know and of
course the finance that um next meeting
we will be bringing in a uh note for the
city hall renovation because last year
when we did this it was for 12 months.
We're coming up on the 12 months. So, we
are with bond council's help to uh
create a new 12-month note until cuz
we're noting it for 12 months until we
find out what the actual amount will be
before we do anything permanent in
financing to see as we get into an older
building. We don't know what we're going
to find. Knock on wood, everything runs
smoothly. Um but I just want to let you
know that we're bringing in um
legislation for a 12-month note. It's
just going to say not to exceed the
attorney decided to do 7 million. That
doesn't mean that's what we're going to
borrow. We're going to be talking with
the administration on what's happened
now. What's the and see if what that
amount will be. I really don't think
it's going to be that. It may it'll be
less than that, but um bond council
wanted to give us room not knowing where
we were. So that it's just written not
to exceed does not mean that's what
we're borrowing, but um we'll be
bringing that in um next council
meeting.
>> I can go for three readings when it
comes.
>> Okay.
>> Chief,
>> good evening, members of council. Um,
I'm here before you tonight to give you
a brief report on a tragic incident that
happened on the city's east side last
week. Um, early in the morning of April
the 1st, we received a 911 call. Um, a
person reporting a house fully engulfed
by fire. Uh, shortly after the call came
in, an officer from the Langston Police
Department arrived. They began to relay
critical information to the responding
firefighters. They also assisted our
heroic neighbors who jumped into action
and saved the lives of two people. When
Langster firefighters arrived, we
initiated an aggressive
fire attack and primary search and
rescue for any victims. Tragically,
three people lost their lives.
We know our community mourns for them.
We mourn with them. Our thoughts and
prayers are with the families and
everybody affected by that incident.
Our
fire investigators have gathered and are
analyzing a large amount of data.
We've already learned many things about
this incident, but fire consumes
evidence and hides some of those
answers. We may we may never fully know
exactly what happened that evening.
This incident is still under
investigation.
Uh we will release more details uh once
that incident or once the investigation
concludes. And we want to thank the
community for their patience during this
time.
>> Thanks Chief. Good evening uh members of
council. I was uh asked after last
week's safety committee to give an
update as well on the uh police
department's involvement with the uh
fire incident that Chief Schulz just
described. Really, I have nothing to add
that he hasn't already added other than
the fact that uh the city departments
collaborated very well as always. Um
fire department, gas department, police
department, even water after the fact.
um we all work together to get to a
resolution and any resources that we
have, any investigative resources that
we have, anything uh that the fire
department needs to continue with their
investigation, they will be they will be
given and have been given. So that's the
only update I have. Thank you.
>> Thanks.
>> Any additional
department updates?
Seeing none, I'll defer to President
Porter for meeting prep. Thank you,
Chairman Skunover. Um, for this
evening's meeting prep, we're going to
go a little bit out of um the regular
order of business. Everybody will see
that there's a special presentation on
tonight from Cryle Communications
regarding city branding. We're going to
do that now. Um, with us tonight is
Angela Cryle. And I'm going to turn this
over to the mayor to do the
introduction.
So many of you may know that in uh 2024
2025 we uh issued a new mission and
vision statement as well as pillars of
service for the city and then uh we
undertook a look at the city's logo and
branding uh late last year and we asked
uh cry communications to do some work
for us and Angela's going to explain
that but what the thought process was is
to update a the city logo So it has some
meaning, but also uh in conjunction with
that a tagline which I feel is a call to
service. So without taking away from
Angela's presentation, I'll turn it over
to her.
>> Thank you, mayor. Um thank you members
of city council for having me here
today. This is the first time in my life
I've addressed city council, so this is
kind of exciting. Um as mayor said, uh
we we were charged with um several
different things over the years. um
actually worked with city council um to
do some um visioning for uh priorities a
couple of years ago. Um and then we have
worked with the city of Lancaster for
some internal mission and vision and
pillars of service. And so these are
things that the city um internally has
been using with employees um to really
rally them around the a similar mission,
a similar vision and how they should
serve the people of our community. Um
you've probably seen this pillars of
service. I know Harry has it hanging in
her office. Um that was the result of
that that um exercise with the employees
of the city. The mayor charged us with
um a charge of creating a new brand for
the city of Lancaster. Um the goals of
this brand would be to create a rally
cry for city employees, residents,
businesses and organizations and
employees of those businesses and
organizations to be proud of and to take
care of our city. Um we wanted it to be
unique from other entities in our
community and color and imagery yet
aligned. Um so many cities go with the
colors of their school district and yet
we also have other districts in our city
um limits that have different colors. So
sometimes having the school colors isn't
isn't exactly the um most um
encompassing. Um so that was one of the
things that we wanted to look at. And
then we wanted it to be a symbol that
city employees would be proud of
displaying. Um and we wanted something
that was uniquely Lancaster.
So, we did this um big process that
started actually in the fall of 2025 um
where we started with an in input
session that convened um department
heads and former city leadership and
others um in a uh variety of branding
activities. Um I'll spare you the
details, but it was quite fun and
engaging and we had a a great time
listening and learning um what people
were proud of and I'll share some of
that output here in a moment. We did a
community survey through the chamber of
commerce to really verify what we heard
um from those city employees or or or
tell us to course correct. Um in this
case it did verify what we had heard. Um
then we did global research on city
branding trends. So we have done city
branding and community branding. We just
finished a branding project for Harlem
Township up in Delaware County um last
month. Um and so we've done that for
other cities, but we also reached out to
other entities throughout the the um
country and really looked at their
branding and what is on trend right now.
What are people doing in terms of
branding? Because we want something
that's going to stand the test of time
and if we have something that's already
outdated when we create it, we're
wasting your resources. So um then we
had an internal um research and um uh
brand identity brainstorming and we
engaged a relatively new person in our
community. Her name is Kylie Lovey. She
is a graphic designer who has designed
for brands across the country. Um she
was super excited to engage in this
process. She's a young person, so that
was also another lens that came um into
play. And then we had five um different
professionals on our team with a variety
of backgrounds and a variety of um
engagement with the city. We had someone
that our our executive vice president
actually lives in Warthingington and
commutes to Lancaster for work. So she
was engaged. Lifelong Fairfield County
girl with a business in Lancaster. I was
engaged. Beth Craft, who a lot of you
know, who is a lifelong resident here,
engaged. So, we had a great variety of
ages and and backgrounds um in that
group that did the internal con
conceptualizing. And then we worked with
Carrie and the mayor, the safety service
director and um the mayor to uh finalize
after we came up with a couple of
different options what we wanted the
brand to be. We made some modifications
to that and then what you are seeing
tonight is the final result of this
journey. Um, a little bit of additional
context that we were able to pull in
because we are a local entity. Um, we
did do the parks think big project. So,
we had that as a lens. We did the city
council planning session last year. We
work for Lancaster city schools. We work
with destination downtown Lancaster. We
work with Lancaster Festival and
numerous boards um or I'm sorry,
businesses and agencies and nonprofits
across the the community. And so, all of
that information was in our brains um as
we were doing this work. This is what we
heard. Um, we heard these are the words,
the concepts, the attributes, the
feelings. We played with some crayons to
get people thinking with the other sides
of their brains to help us understand
what colors they liked, what colors felt
like Lancaster to them. Um, and so
that's why there's crayons up here
because those are the results of the
yeses um in the the yes, no, and maybe
piles. Um, but you can see the words
that came to bear as we were looking at
the input that we received throughout.
Rather than giving you a big document
that outlines all of this information,
you can see what people really really
resonated with. Um, and so we um were
given the call to by the mayor and
Carrie to create a call to action with a
tagline that first was a call to action
for us as residents to take pride in our
city and create a welcoming space
because if we don't love it and we don't
own it, then nobody else is going to
care about it and nobody else is going
to want to be here. So, and then
secondarily to be an invitation to
visit, experience and enjoy our
community. So, the result of that, um,
some of you saw this at the state of the
city. Um, it was a bit of a teaser about
how much we love our history, our
people, our businesses, our nonprofits.
If you look at that heart-shaped wordle
that I showed you before, many of these
words are on there. Um, our visitors,
our employees, our partners, we love our
Lancaster. And so, our tagline um that
is going to be used um on city um
signage and whatnot will be love our
Lancaster.
So then the second part of this is the
imagery. And um as you saw in those
crayons, we use um color psychology in
some of the work that we do with
branding. And so we used those words to
help um inform what kinds of colors we
would use. So we have blues and greens.
Surprisingly, lots of people in this
town are really proud of our water and
our water supply. And so that was one of
the things that Carrie and I were like,
"Wow, that's really cool to know that
people are proud of water." But they
are. Um, so you'll see some blue greens
which also are balance and stability and
refreshing. We have some dark darker
blues and blue violets that are security
and reliability and deep, creative,
innovative, imaginative. Then you'll see
some yellows and shades of yellow that
are clarity, happiness, optimism, and
hope. And you'll see some greens which
are calm, trust, health, and prosperity.
As I said before, we did a lot of
research on um branding trends. And one
thing that you're seeing across the
board in all design work is um
iconography, which is basically the use
of icons that represent a community. Um
and so we were seeing a lot of that not
just in municipal brands, but also
across the board with um with for-profit
and nonprofit brands. And so this was
the inspiration for the imagery of the
logo.
This photo in particular, which is um
taken basically right out that door, um
of the fountain and the clock tower
where they almost cross over and become
one, um is actually the the photo that
really inspired the combination of the
iconography and this photo to create
this brand, which you can see. This is
just the black and white version, but
you can see that is a fused clock tower
and fountain where the the water spurts
of the fountain are the the round
windows of the clock tower. And so it is
uniquely Lancaster. Um it is two icons
that we heard over and over and over
again cause people to imagine the city
and think of the city from an imagery
perspective. And so Kylie, this amazing
umly talented graphic designer that we
worked with, created this image for us.
Um this is it in color. You'll see it.
Um the aqua color um the color that
represents water is the fountain. And
then the stability and the strength and
the security is the darker blue of the
clock tower.
This is what it would look like in
various forms and formats. The cool
thing about branding now is that you
don't have to just have one way that you
use a logo and you don't have to have
just one color combination that you use
with a logo either. So, um, you'll see
here in a couple, uh, slides where we've
used these different colors in different
ways and used the font and the Lancaster
to put together different ways that we
can use the logo. And the city actually
has all of this already um, in their
files. And they are already starting to
implement it. So, here's some of the
different ways that you can use the
color combination, use the layout um,
and um, kind of infuse your own um,
identity on our overall identity. This
is what it could look like on a
billboard, a shirt. Um, that is the
color palette at the bottom. It's a
little dark, but it's a dark navy blue,
that aqua color, a dark um forest green,
a mint color, and then a cream yellow.
Our next steps is um working with the
law director to um get get things
trademarked. Um doing a slow strategic
roll out as city resources allow. We
want to be good stewards of taxpayer
dollars. We're not going to rush out and
replace every single city sign, every
single trash can. Um, all of that. Um,
the circle icon in the middle of Main
Street, that's due for paving what mayor
in 2030, 2028 sometime soon. So, all of
those things will gradually take place.
This is not a big ta. Everything is now
this logo. It will be a slow burn roll
out um as as the opportunities arise.
And that is it.
Yeah. Oh, sure. So, what you see in a
Wordle, Carrie asked me to explain how
this works. What you see in this Wordle
is it's weighted by the the amount of
times that we heard those words. Um, and
there are some words that are repeated,
you'll see, because they were parts of
other words or they were repeated many,
many times. Um, but really the biggest
word we heard from people was historic.
Um, followed by city hall, history,
downtown. Amanda Everett should be super
excited that downtown was mentioned many
times. um fountain um Mount Pleasant. Um
and honestly, we did play with Mount
Pleasant as an icon a lot. We really
tried to incorporate that, but when you
have a brown cliff,
it's very in it's not distinguishable at
all. Um so we did play with that. We
tried. Um but what really hit home was
that fountain and that that city hall
together.
>> Any any questions?
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Back to me.
>> Yep.
>> All right. Do we have any other
discussion items for finance?
Seeing none, I'll ask for a motion to
adjourn.
>> So moved.
>> Second.
>> We are adjourned at 6:38.
>> The regular meeting of Lancaster City
Council will commence at 6:45.
Daddy.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 74-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
Life moves fast and Buckeye is here to
keep you moving. New dream job?
Celebrate with a ride that feels just as
exciting. Passing the keys to your new
teen driver? Treat yourself to an
upgrade you'll love. Family getting
bigger? Buckeye's got the perfect
spacious, safety packed vehicle for
every new arrival. Wherever life takes
you, Buckeye Nissan, Georgeesville
Nissan, Buckeye Honda, and Buckeye
Toyota are ready to drive you forward.
Your life, your car, your choice. Choose
Buckeye.
Ladies and gentlemen, please rise if
you're able and join us in a moment of
prayer. God, grant us the serenity to
accept the things that we cannot change,
the courage to change the things we can,
and finally, and most importantly, the
wisdom to know the difference. Please
join me in the pledge of allegiance.
>> I pledge algiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands, one nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
>> Call the April 6, 2026 Lancaster City
Council meeting to order. Please call
the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> here.
>> Mr. Bisjack
>> Mr. Carr
>> here.
>> Miss Cowwood
>> Mrs. Hoop
>> here.
>> Mr. Nisley
>> Mr. Og
>> here.
>> Mr. Skunover
>> Miss Smiley
>> here.
>> And Mr. Sullie
>> here. Let the record reflect that all 10
members of Lancaster City Council are
present uh this evening. Reading and
disposing of the journal.
>> I have regular meeting minutes dated
March 23rd, 2026.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
receive and file the journal. All those
in favor, please signify by saying I. I.
I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Reports of
city officials.
>> I have email dated April 2nd, 2026
regarding planning commission meeting
April 9th submitted by city planner
Chassen Carter.
>> Just one.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
receive and file the reports of city
officials. All those in favor uh please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed same sign.
Communications.
>> I have two or three this the I'm sorry I
have two a series of emails between
Melody Bobbit Larry Als Amy Cohen and
Robert Nicely dated March 24th through
the 31st 2026 regarding feathered flags
in Lancaster. I have Neil dated April
2nd, 2026 regarding the Prowleywood LLC
transfer of liquor license um from the
Ohio Department of Commerce.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the communications.
Second.
>> A motion and second to receive and file
the communications. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. We have no
special presentation uh or awards this
evening. We have no petitions and
memorials. Uh we've now reached the time
uh for permission of voters and
taxpayers to address council. Briefly,
the rules are you get three minutes to
speak. You should be a voter or a
taxpayer of the city of Lancaster. You
need to put your name and address on the
um signin sheet and introduce yourself
to council.
Good evening, city administrators and
council members. My name is Brian
Everett. I'll finish filling this out
when I'm done talking. I'm not smart
enough to do two things at the same
time. Um, I'm a resident here in
Langster. I live at 201 South High
Street. And as I'm sure you are all
aware last week, in addition to the
horrific home fire, uh, also saw a crash
on Lincoln Avenue where a child was, uh,
severely injured. Uh I have not heard an
update as to his condition, but um
severely injured while riding a bike and
being hit by a vehicle. Uh the initial
reports show that the driver of the
vehicle was not impaired. Um nor did,
from my understanding, it indicate that
they're uh they were speeding or there
was anything else readily apparent to
the officer on the scene with respect to
the cause of the crash. But I think that
brings my point uh even more in focus
because our streets should be safe for
all of the residents of our community.
And for an 11-year-old kid who might do
something stupid on a bike like
11-year-olds do or for an adult riding a
bike who may be momentarily distracted
or have to swerve to avoid something, it
shouldn't be a death sentence. Uh we
should design complete streets. It took
decades to get to where we are, where we
have unnecessarily wide streets upon
which uh vehicles travel uh in excessive
speed um and produce way too dangerous
of a situation. Um, and I would just
implore city council to as they look
forward to any street work, whether it's
Main Street in 2030 or whether it's a
side street that most people don't give
any thought to unless they live on it,
to look at complete streets and design
them for all users. Uh, this kid
couldn't be in a bike lane because there
isn't a bike lane. This kid couldn't
even ride on the sidewalk because
Lincoln, for the great majority of it,
from Memorial Drive out does not have
sidewalks. If it does have sidewalks,
there's no differentiating height.
There's no curbs. There's no separation.
This is unfortunately, and it's not the
fault of anybody in this room, it's from
decades. This was set up to happen,
which is why the standards for
journalism don't call these things
accidents. They call them crashes
because it wasn't an accident. The
street was designed for this to happen.
Thank you.
Hi, council. Melody Bobett, 1852 Frank
Drive, Lancaster.
Uh, first off, I want to thank all of
you who responded to my email that I
sent in regards to the feathered flags.
It is something that is um greatly
concerning to me. Since I only have
three minutes, I'm going to be brief
though. Two weeks ago here in city
council, it was mentioned that we would
have further discussions about the
feather flags. I do plan on being at
code enforcement meeting tomorrow
morning.
Uh, in my email to you, I express my
desire that you do not make any changes
to our current city ordinance and these
feathered flags. Um, in my email, I
expressed many reasons why we shouldn't.
One of the reasons why I put in there
was noise pollution. To you and I, this
noise pollution may mean absolutely
nothing. But to those who do not have
sight, it means quite a bit. I'm going
to reiterate that. To those who do not
have sight, those feathered flags and
the noise pollution that they make means
quite a bit. You may not be aware, but
at the corner, the crossroads of Fair
and Pierce,
you probably, if you're listening well,
can hear the tones of the light.
Those were put there because of the
residents that live in the area that do
not have sight.
We used to have feathered flags in this
city. And if you're if you know the
intersection, every corner is a
commercial lot.
If every commercial lot puts those signs
up,
the blind cannot hear the tones of the
light.
We do not want that back in Lancaster.
Plan to discuss it further, like I said,
at tomorrow's meeting.
Um, but I would appreciate
all the meetings Thursday,
the 9th. Okay, my mistake. All right,
I'll have to change my calendar. Be
there the night. But, um, I'd like every
one of you around the table to, um, make
certain that this receives no further
traction. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Is there any further um,
public comment this evening?
Hearing none, we thank you for attending
tonight's meeting. Reports of standing
committees.
>> I have three this evening. Safety
committee meeting agenda dated March
31st, 2026, submitted by Mr. Bisjack.
Administrative services committee
meeting um rescheduled from May 8th to
May 22nd, 2026. Submitted by Miss Cohen.
Finance committee meeting agenda and
meeting minutes um dated April 6, 2026.
Submitted by Mr. Scooter.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to receive
and file the reports of standing
committees. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those post, same sign. Reports of
special committees.
>> There are no reports this evening.
>> No public hearing this evening. We will
now move on to the reading of
resolutions. Beginning with the third
reading of temporary resolution 3526. a
resolution to authorize the service
safety director to readvertise for bids
and enter into a contract for
construction of the East 6th Avenue
Bridge over Feder's Run replacement
project and to hire a consultant to
provide construction inspection services
and to declare an emergency. This is
through public works committee Mr. Carr
and Mr. Pidgeot. This Jack
>> Council member Carr.
>> Mr. President, I would like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record resolution
temporarily numbered 35-26.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to pass
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 3526. Any
discussion? Council member Carr.
>> Just to summarize that this is to put
the project back out to bid given that
we only had one bid that was more than
20% over the original uh engineers
estimates.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary resolution
3526 passes 10 to zero. We'll now move
on to the second reading of resolutions,
beginning with temporary resolution
3826.
a resolution authorizing the mayor to
act on behalf of the city of Lancaster
and enter into any and all agreements or
settlements necessary to participate in
the new national opioid settlements with
the Associated Pharmacies Incorporated
and American Associated Pharmacies, JM
Corporation, Louisiana Wholesale Drug
Company, Morrison and and Dixon Company,
North Carolina Mutual Wholesale Drug
Company Incorporated, and United Natural
Foods Incorporated,
including its subsidiaries,
Super Value and Advantage Logistics, and
to declare an emergency. This is through
law committee, Miss Smiley and Mr. Al.
>> Council member Smiley.
>> Second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 3826.
Temporary resolution 3926.
A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to wave the request for
qualifications and negotiate a design
build contract for energy upgrade grant
for the south water treatment plant
rehabilitation and to declare an
emergency. This through water water
pollution control committee Mr. Als and
Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Als.
>> Uh yes, Mr. President. I move that we
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of resolution temporarily number
3926.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution 3926.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend
council member?
>> Not at this point.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes. Motion to suspend the rules and
wave the third reading of temporary
resolution 3926 passes 10 to zero.
Council member Als.
>> Yes, Mr. President. I move that we pass
and engross and enter upon the written
record resolution temporarily numbered
3926.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and a second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 3926. Any
discussion? Council member AS.
>> Just as a reminder, we um applied for
this grant in 2025.
Uh it's a 50% match. We budgeted for our
50%. Um a lot of good work's going to be
done at the Southwater treatment plant.
Um I would encourage you to pass it.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Miss Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes. Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes. Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Solid,
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
3926 passes 10 to zero.
>> We'll now move on to the first reading
of resolutions beginning with temporary
resolution 4026.
>> A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and to amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor and the sanitation fund
for the purchase of a new front load
garbage truck and to declare an
emergency. This is through service
committee, Mr. Nisley and Mrs. Hoop.
>> Council member Nisley.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Um, this
legislation just uh appropriates the
funds necessary for the city to purchase
a new frontload garbage truck that was
uh that was involved in an accident back
in February. Um, this legislation came
to become due to the fact that we have a
uh we have the the wrecked vehicle that
is currently in the shop being assessed
for repairs. They seem to be going up
and up and up. Uh the city's currently
renting a garbage truck to fulfill this
route that's costing the city $8,900 a
year and um so the it's we the city
deems it necessary to pass this
legislation and purchase a new vehicle
so that way um that would save the city
some money. So thank you Mr. Mr.
President. This will be the first of two
readings.
>> Thank you.
>> And and council member will be my
second.
>> You said $8,900 a year
>> a month. My apologies. A month.
So, first of two readings and Okay, we
got it. Thank you.
That concludes our reading of
resolutions. Now, we'll move on to the
reading of ordinances, beginning with
the third reading of temporary ordinance
526,
>> an ordinance to amend permanent
ordinance 63-25,
the management pay ordinance to add an
assistant prosecutor position for a
limited period of time and to declare an
emergency. Mr. Finance Committee, Mr.
Skunover, and Mr. Sully. Council member
Skun over.
>> Yes, Mr. President. I'd like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 526.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second uh to pass
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary ordinance 526. Any discussion?
Council member Skun.
>> Um just a brief reminder. the law
director asked for this part-time while
this additional assistant um prosecutor
she has one that's looking to early
retire and another one that will be out
uh on FMLA. So we she wants to fill this
position uh get them trained before
those other two things happen.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion
hearing? None. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes. Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Temporary ordinance 526
passes 10 to zero. Temporary ordinance
626.
>> An ordinance authorizing the service
safety director to execute a lease
amendment with the Park National Bank
and to declare an emergency. this
through law committee, Miss Carr and Mr.
OG.
>> Council member Carr.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
the council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record
um ordinance temporarily numbered 6-26.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and second to pass gross
and enter upon the written record.
Temporary ordinance 6-26.
Any discussion? Council member Carr.
>> Just to summarize, this is to amend the
lease on the property the city owns on
Memorial Drive. um where Park Nationals
uh parking lot sits right now to amend
it to a
uh 50-year lease um designating the
escalators on the lease. And if there's
any other questions, I guess we can
direct those to Law Director Hall if
anyone has questions.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the roll.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes. Mr. OG,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Miss Smiley,
>> abstain.
>> And Mr. Salty,
>> yes.
>> Temporary ordinance 6-26 passes 9 to
zero with one abstension.
We'll now move on to the second reading
of ordinances beginning with temporary
ordinance 7-26.
>> An ordinance to accept the final plat
for the Victory Commons development.
This through code enforcement code
enforcement and zoning committee. Mr.
Sully and Mr. Nisley. Council member
Sie,
>> second of three readings, please.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance 7-26.
Now move on to first reading of
ordinances beginning with temporary
ordinance 8-26.
>> An ordinance to vacate city easements
for the Maran Development Averia senior
assisted living facility and to declare
an emergency. Um this is through the law
committee, Miss Smiley and Mr. Skover.
Council member Smiley.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I would like
to make a motion that council suspend
its rules
and wave the second and third readings
of
resol or
>> temporary ordinance or ordinance
temporarily numbered 8-26.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
suspend the rules and wave the second
and third reading of temporary ordinance
8-26.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
just that this project is something that
is one of a kind so far in Lancaster and
the suspension of this will allow them
um to be able to make their bond
issuance deadline by April 15th and if
they do not they might miss some
critical deadlines for um their
contractual and development deadlines
after that.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion
hearing? None. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes. Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> no.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third reading of temporary
ordinance 8-26 passes 82.
>> Council member Smiley.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I would like
to make a motion that council pass
engross and enter upon the written
record uh ordinance temporarily numbered
8-26.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary ordinance 8-26.
Any further discussion on the ordinance?
Council member SM. This ordinance is
addressing the a development by Marian
um that is a senior living development
out on Sloum in West 7th and they are
requesting council's approval to vacate
three easements on the property to be
able to move forward.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes. Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> M or Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary ordinance
8-26
passes 10 to zero.
>> That concludes our reading of uh
legislation this evening. We have no
tabled legislation. Um do we have any
unfinished business uh before council
this evening?
Um, we now move on to new business, uh,
which, uh, we do have a liquor, uh,
license, a request to transfer. Um, so
do you want to go ahead and read that
into the record?
>> Yep. I, um, have a transfer permit
number one4362-01.
It's a transfer from Suss LLC to
Prelywood LLC on 434 North Columbus
Street, Lancaster. So, this would be a
transfer of ownership. Law Director
Hall, is there any there any objections
at this point?
>> Um, none for me. I believe uh everybody
should have seen the email that the
clerk sent out with the information from
Chief Snider. Um, looks like the
typical, you know, kind of things that
that you can expect to see from that
type of establishment, but certainly
nothing um, you know, excessive or
anything like that. So, no objections
from from me or law enforcement. Thank
you.
>> Okay. Thank you.
And then I know we discussed last week
the last one that we did the objection
on uh that we processed the objection.
Were we able to verify whether or not
for purposes of a yearly renewal we have
an opportunity to object at that point?
>> So I did I did check with the clerk. We
haven't received any renewal notices for
the last I believe two years now. Um,
and so I opened a case on the Division
of Liquor Control's website, um,
indicating that, you know, we don't know
where they're going, but they're going
someplace else. Um, the Division of
Liquor Control never responded to me
directly, but I got a very generic email
indicating that, um, they're trying to
move everything online to an online
database, and in order to see any of
those things in the future, um, we're
going to have to have some kind of
profile and login in order to do that.
Um the clerk indicated that she was
willing to go ahead and sign up for that
so that she could obtain that
information for city council as a whole
and so she anticipates doing that in the
near future. Um I assume so. Uh yeah, at
that point then obviously we won't have
to rely on the division of liquor
control sending those to us and getting
them to the clerk of council.
>> Okay. Thank you very much. Appreciate
it.
>> So I'll entertain a motion or we do do
we need to even we don't have to do
anything with it, do we? We just let it
go. If you want to do a voice vote to um
to not object, you're more than welcome
to do that or to, you know, to authorize
or approve or whatever you'd like. Um if
you take no action, it just happens. So,
it's your call.
>> Okay. Thank you. Um I'll just we'll take
a voice vote on just the um is allowing
the transfer to proceed. Can I have a
>> All those in favor?
>> Please.
>> Second.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So, um, all those in favor, please
signify by saying, "I."
>> I.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Um, additionally, in new business this
evening, um, we do have to appoint a
member of council to the SID board. Um,
I do believe there's a motion um, uh,
for, uh, an appointment.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I motion
to appoint Elena Hoop to the Destination
Downtown Lancaster Special Improvement
Board.
>> Second.
>> Oh, sorry.
>> Okay.
It was Larry.
>> Larry.
>> Larry seconded. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> So, we thank you for serving on that
board. And I'm sure you'll want to talk
to the executive director soon about
their next meeting. So, um, new
business. Uh, we can do committee
updates. We'll start with Council Member
Sie.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. We'll have a
we have a meeting April 9th at 7:30 a.m.
in the 1897 conference room.
>> Code enforcement.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> All right. Uh safety committee. Uh I got
a little bit of an update here. We had a
meeting last Friday, so I'll be as brief
as I can, though. Um starting with the
police department. We had a staffing
update. Two officers have uh are now
currently at the municipal court
full-time with one uh also being
deployed to the Middle East. Uh
currently the police department is
trying to secure a $48,000 firehouse
subs grant for AEDs within the
department. Uh Chief Snder also shared
some statistics uh year-over-year
comparison. Uh specifically the police
departments received 48,000 calls.
Burglaries are down for uh 53%. Uh auto
injuries have also decreased.
specifically uh serious injuries have
decreased by 50% with minor uh uh auto
accidents and injuries uh decreasing by
13%.
And then also Chief Snder also shared
that the police department will be
getting one new uh cruiser for this
year. Moving on to the fire department.
Uh currently right now there's going to
be anticipated legislation coming up
here for the second meeting in April. Uh
there was a uh retirement an unexpected
retirement that came up within the last
two weeks. The legislation initially was
uh slated to look like it was going to
be a transfer of funds for in the amount
of $60,000. It's now looking more like
$43,000 to uh facilitate this
retirement. Uh on top of that too, the
fire department is working with app
architecture to finalize the footprint
and layouts of engine house 2. Uh and
then also on top of that coming up with
some potential costs for the various
stages of uh construction. And then
lastly, there's going to also be
legislation to move money uh from the
purchase order for the architect. Uh
currently the legislation was slated for
just 2025, but now that we're in 2026,
in order to make sure the books are
clean and we're following government
accounting practices uh appropriately,
we're going to have to close the 2025
purchase order. The money then is going
to go transfer into the unencumbered
balance of the general fund. And then
that money then is going to go to a 2026
purchase order to provide for that uh
legislation and allow for that design
work to continue. So I know it's a
little convoluted, but want to
communicate that it's essentially not
new money, just transferring everything
that way. Uh so yeah, that's uh my
report for the safety committee. Thank
you, Mr. President.
>> Thank you, Council Member Cohen.
>> Uh no report. My next meeting,
administrative services, is May 22nd,
which is a change, um, at 2 PM in the
conference room.
>> Thank you, Council Member Als.
>> The Water Water Pollution Control
Committee will meet Friday morning at
7:30 and a little update on Bowowers
Park. Um,
we are waiting for a contract. Uh, we've
finally
the Ohio engineers are gone. and they've
vacated the property. They're no longer
doing any work there. And what the city,
what the parks department has said is
we're we're taking the project over and
we're going to finish the project.
That's a very 30,000 foot review, but
it's going to happen.
Maybe in my lifetime,
I hope. Thank you.
>> Thank you for your update, Council
Member Smiley. No committee update yet,
but our next committee meeting is on
April 17th at 12:30 in the 1897
conference room.
>> Thank you, Council Member Og.
>> Uh, nothing to report that hasn't
already been shared.
>> Thank you, Council Member Skunover.
>> Um, not quite to do with finance
committee, but I did get a phone call
today and then saw a post. I kind of
briefly brought it up to service safety
director and I promised that I would
mention on the floor. So, utility bills.
Um, I got a phone call. I checked my
utility bill. So, the and I couldn't
find a notice where it was. So, I'm like
giving everybody else a heads up that's
not on Facebook because it's got gained
a lot of traction. So, the dates are due
dates have moved. So, I've like my
bill's always been due on the 18th and
all of a sudden this month it's due on
the 14th. So, if you don't look at your
bill and it's autopay,
you you might want to make sure that
you're prepared for that. So, I don't I
know that uh the utility department
director was out today. So, hopefully
unless the mayor or Carrie have come up
with something new since we started this
meeting. Just kind of wanted to throw it
out there. Sorry to put you on the spot,
but I said I would bring it up. So,
>> thank you. I don't know what's going on.
Thank you.
>> I saw the same post. We We'll check and
and get an answer. I'm not sure what
what happened there.
>> Okay. Council member PR.
>> Um, no. Pending legislation for public
works. Uh, with tonight's vote moving
forward on the rebid of the Sixth Avenue
project, street improvement program
proceeds as well as Arbor Valley Drive.
And our next U meeting is Friday, uh,
April 17th at 7:30 a.m. Thank you,
Council Member Nley.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. The next
meeting of service committee will be May
14th. Um, the only update I have is on
the legislation that we're currently
that we just introduced today on the uh
the purchase of a new uh garbage vehicle
for the sanitation department. Um, and I
just want to say I thank um, council
member Skunover for bringing up the
utility collection uh, due date issue.
That was something that was brought to
my attention as well and I was going to
mention it here tonight. So, um, thanks
for broaching that subject and we will
hopefully have some answers by the next
meeting.
>> Thank you, Council Member Hoop.
>> Um, with economic development, we don't
have a lot going on, but we do have a
meeting later on in April. So,
>> thank you. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Gary, Mr. Mayor, you guys
have anything?
>> I've got something for new business. I
just want to give a little background on
the uh Mrs. Bobbit spoke about feathered
flags and I know Councilman Nisley has a
proposed change in legislation for the
new council members who were not on the
previous council. Um
about four years ago, we formed a a
committee of a couple of dozen
individuals including myself and Mr.
Skunover representing council, um
members of the community, a lot of
people that would be involved in uh code
enforcement, zoning decisions and we
went through the zoning code significant
and rather intensely over uh several
months and the feathered flag topic came
up at that at those meetings which were
public and a lot of discussion went into
the pros and cons and yeah, Mrs. Bob
referred to uh one of the cons uh of the
the noise they create, but they also
create several other issues that I think
we discussed at these meetings uh
several years ago. And understand that
legislation
uh is is new legislation. It's not been
on the books for 30 years or anything
like that. It's been on the books for
like two and a half years, three years.
So during these meetings, one of the
things that came to light is and we had
our code enforcement people present at
these meetings. Enforcement. So they put
out a feathered flag. It's supposed to
be for a grand opening. The grand
opening lasts three years. It never
comes down. It's tattered, torn. It's in
the rightway. Uh I know we discussed
about appropriate um enforcement
measures that might be enacted in in the
legislation.
We have
small
uh zoning uh enforcement
uh crew, I should say. Looking for a
word there. Uh it's two people. It's a
zoning violation. So, they would have to
track the date that the feather flag
went in
and then follow up after the time period
permitted.
Then they would send the warning, etc.,
etc., etc. It creates an a significant
amount of work for something that I will
tell you until Mr. Nisley brought it up.
No member of the community has
approached me on. I'm not sure if
they've approached you on it, but I've
heard have no no correspondence in in
the time that this has been enacted. And
understand, we've enforced this since
the time it was enacted, and we've had
nobody calling for them to be permitted.
Not saying that there aren't a few
people that would like to have them as a
I think they probably are a good
advertisement tool. They also distract
drivers.
They also block vision. They also get
tattered and torn and they stay out well
beyond any intended original purpose
because people just decide not to remove
them. So, I just thought I would tell
you a little background of how we got to
where we're at and why we enacted that
uh ban on feathered flags.
It wasn't done
willy-nilly, so to speak. It was done
with a lot of thought and effort and
decision-m that went into it and with
people arguing the pros of them at that
at those public meetings.
>> So, there's your background.
>> Thank you.
>> I have no updates, but thank you.
>> Thank you. Announcement of scheduled
meetings. I have next regular sessions
of council April 20th, 2026 at 6:30m
here in council chambers. And during
that council meeting, we'll have um two
presentations, one from NOPEC and one
for tree commission. Um and then again
on maple maple I'm thinking trees May
4th, 2026 at 6:30 p.m. here in council
chambers.
>> Okay.
No special scheduled meetings. Regularly
scheduled committee meetings.
>> I have five of them. Code enforcement
and zoning committee, April 9th, 2026 at
7:30 a.m. in the 1897 conference room in
city hall. Water pollution control
committee, April 10th, 2026 at 7:30 a.m.
1897 conference room in city hall.
Public works committee meeting April
17th at 7:30 a.m. 1897 conference room
city hall. Law Committee meeting April
17th, 2026 at 12:30 p.m. and 1897
conference room in city hall and
economic development committee meeting
April 30th, 2026 at 7:30 a.m. 1897
conference room city hall.
>> Thank you. Reading of bills.
>> I have one from MNCO, publication of
permanent ordinance 4-26 for $65.78.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
we pay the bill.
>> Second. Motion, a second to pay bill.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. We have no
need for an executive session. I didn't
entertain a motion to adjourn.
>> Mr. President, I will make that motion
to adjurnn.
>> Second. A motion, a second to adjurnn.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. If uh you
have legislation to sign, please stay
and make sure we get your signatures.
Thank you.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 740-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
>> Life moves fast and Buckeye is here to
keep you moving. New dream job?
Celebrate with a ride that feels just as
exciting. Passing the keys to your new
teen driver? Treat yourself to an
upgrade you'll love. Family getting
bigger? Buckeye's got the perfect
spacious, safety packed vehicle for
every new arrival. Wherever life takes
you, Buckeye Nissan, Georgeesville
Nissan, Buckeye Honda, and Buckeye
Toyota are ready to drive you forward.
Your life, your car, your choice. Choose
Buckeye.